有些故事如史诗般 惊险万分
Some stories are so epic with such high stakes that - in my head -
在我脑海中似乎出现了星球大战电影开头的滑动文本
it's like the crawling text at the start of a Star Wars movie.
你知道的 就像
You know, like -
“第一集 操作系统大战”
Episode 1. The OS Wars.
是的 就像那样子
Yeah, like that.
这是一个局势加剧紧张的时期
It is a period of mounting tensions.
比尔·盖茨与史蒂夫·乔布斯的帝国
The empires of Bill Gates and Steve Jobs
发起了一场无可避免的专有软件之战
careen to ward an inevitable battle of proprietary software.
盖茨与 IBM 结成了强大的联盟
Gates has formed a powerful alliance with IBM,
而乔布斯则拒绝开放他的硬件和操作系统授权
while Jobs refuses to license his hardware or operating system.
他们争夺统治地位的战争 简直席卷了操作系统的“银河系”
Their battle for dominance threatens to engulf the galaxy in an OS war.
与此同时 在这些“帝王们”所不知道的偏远之地
Meanwhile, in distant lands, and unbeknownst of the emperors,
信奉开源的“反叛者们”开始聚集
open source rebels have begun to gather.
好吧 这也许有点戏剧性
Okay. Maybe that's a bit dramatic,
但当我们谈论上世纪八九十年代和 2000 年左右的操作系统之争时
but when we're talking about the OS wars at the 1980s, 90s and 2000s,
这也不算言过其实
it's hard to overstate things.
确实曾经发生过一场史诗级的统治之战
There really was an epic battle for dominance.
史蒂夫·乔布斯和比尔·盖茨确实掌握着许多人的命运
Steve Jobs and Bill Gates really did hold the fates of billions in their hands.
掌控了操作系统
Control the operating system,
你就掌握了绝大多数人使用计算机的方式
and you control how the vast majority of people use computers.
互相通讯的方式、获取信息的方式
How we communicate with each other. How we source information.
我可以一直罗列下去 不过你知道我的意思
I could go on but you know all this.
掌握了操作系统 你就是帝王
Control the OS, and you would be an emperor.
我是 Saron Yitbarek 你现在收听的是代码英雄
I'm Saron Yitbarek, and you are listening to Command Line Heroes,
一款红帽公司原创的播客节目
an original podcast from Red Hat.
你问什么是代码英雄？
What is a command line hero, you ask?
嗯 如果你愿意用创造代替使用
Well, if you would rather make something than just use it,
如果你相信开发者拥有构建美好未来的能力
if you believe developers have the power to build a better future,
如果你希望拥有一个大家都有权利用科技塑造生活的世界
if you want a world where we all get a say in how our technology shape our lives,
那么你 我的朋友 就是一位代码英雄
then you, my friend, are a command line hero.
在本系列节目中 我们将为你带来
In this series, we bring you stories of the developers among us
那些“白码起家”改变技术的程序员故事
who were transforming tech from the command line up.
那么我是谁 凭什么指引你踏上这段艰苦的旅程？
And who am I to be guiding you on this track?
Saron Yitbarek 是哪根葱？
Who is Saron Yitbarek?
嗯 事实上我觉得我跟你差不多
Well, actually, I'm guessing I'm a lot like you.
首先 我是一个开发者
I'm a developer for starters,
我做的任何事都依赖于开源软件
and everything I do depends on open source software.
我的世界就是如此
It's my world.
通过在博客中讲故事
The stories we tell on this podcast
我可以跳出无聊的日常工作 鸟瞰全景
are a way for me to get above the daily grind of my work and see that big picture.
希望这对你也一样有用
I hope it does the same thing for you too.
我迫不及待地想知道
What I wanted to know right off the bat was
开源技术从何而来？
where did the open source technology even come from?
我的意思是 我对林纳斯·托瓦兹和 Linux® 的荣耀有一些了解
I mean, I know a fair bit about Linus Torvalds and the glories of Linux®,
我相信你也一样
as I'm sure you do too.
但是说真的 开源并不是一开始就有的对吗？
But really, there was life before open source, right?
如果我想发表对这些最新 最棒的技术
And if I want to truly appreciate the latest and greatest things
比如 DevOps 和容器的感激
like DevOps and containers and on and on,
为了那些早期的开发者 我有义务了解它们从何而来
well, I feel like I owe it to all those earlier developers
to know where this stuff came from.
所以 让我们暂时先不用担心内存泄露和缓冲溢出
So, let's take a short break
from worrying about memory leaks and buffer overflows.
我们的旅程将从操作系统之战开始
Our journey begins with the OS wars,
这是一场波澜壮阔的桌面控制之战
that epic battle for control of the desk top.
这场战争亘古未有 因为：
It was like nothing that the world had ever seen, and I'll tell you why.
首先 在计算机时代
First, in the age of computing,
大公司拥有指数级的规模优势
you've got exponentially scaling advantages for the big fish.
其次 从未有过这么一场控制争夺战是如此变化多端
And second, there's never been such a battle for control
on a ground that's constantly shifting.
比尔·盖茨和史蒂夫·乔布斯? 目前为止他们也不知道事情会如何发展
Bill Gates and Steve Jobs? They don't know it yet,
但是到这个故事进行到一半的时候
but by the time this story is halfway done,
他们所争夺的所有东西都将发生改变、进化
everything they're fighting for is going to change, evolve,
最终上升到云端
and even ascend into the cloud.
好的 让我们回到 1983 年的秋季 还有六年我才出生
Okay. It's the fall of 1983, I was negative six years old.
那时候的总统还是罗纳德·里根
Ronald Regan's the president,
美国和苏联扬言要把地球拖入核战争之中
and the US and the Soviet Union are threatening to drag the planet into nucler war.
在檀香山（火奴鲁鲁）的市政中心
Over the city center of Honolulu,
正在举办一年一度的苹果公司销售会议
it's the annual Apple sales conference.
一群苹果公司的员工正在等待史蒂夫·乔布斯上台
An exclusive bunch of Apple emplyees are waiting for Steve Jobs to get on stage.
他 28 岁 热情洋溢 看起来非常自信
He's the super-bright-eyed twenty-eight-year-old,
and he's looking pretty confident.
乔布斯很严肃地对着麦克风说
In a very serious voice, Jobs speaks into the mic and says
他邀请了三个行业专家
that he's invited three industry experts to have
来就他的软件进行一次小组讨论
a penal discussion on software.
然而随后发生的事情你肯定想不到
But the next thing that happenes is not what you would expect.
超级俗气的 80 年代音乐响彻整个房间
Super cheesy 80s music fills the room,
一堆多彩灯管照亮了舞台
a bunch of multicolored tube lights light up the stage,
然后一个播音员的声音响起
and then an announcer's voice says-
女士们 先生们 现在是麦金塔软件的约会游戏时间
And now, ladies and gentlemen, the Macintosh Software Dating Game.
带着大大的笑容 乔布斯宣布
Jobs has this big grin on his face as he reveals
台上的三个CEO必须轮流向他示好
that the three CEOs on stage have to take turns wooing him.
他简直就是 80 年代科技界的钻石王老五
It's essentially an 80s version of The Bachelor, but for tech love.
两个软件大佬讲完话
Two of the software bigwigs say their bit,
接着轮到了第三个人
and then it's over to contestant number three.
难不成 ？是的
Is that-? Yep.
那是年轻的比尔·盖茨 戴着一服大大的 遮住了半张脸的方框眼镜
A fresh-faced Bill Gates with large square glasses that cover half his face.
他宣称在1984年
He proclaimes that during 1984,
微软一半的收入渠道会来源于麦金塔软件
half of Microsoft's avenue was gonna come from Macintosh Software.
他的这番话引来了观众热情的掌声
The audience loves it, and give him a big round of applause.
但是他们不知道的是 在一个月后
What they don't know is that one month after this event,
比尔·盖茨将会宣布发布 Windows 1.0 的计划
Bill Gates will announce his plans to release Windows 1.0.
你永远也猜不到乔布斯正在跟苹果未来最大的敌人打情骂俏
You'd never guess Jobs is flirting with someone who'd end up as Apple's biggest rival.
但微软和苹果即将举行科技史上最糟糕的婚礼
But Microsoft and Apple are about to live through the worst marriage in tech history.
他们会彼此背叛、相互毁灭
They're going to betray each other, they're going to try and destroy each other,
但又深深地、痛苦地捆绑在一起
and they're going to be deeply, painfully bound to each other.
我猜从哲学角度上来讲 苹果是更理想化、注重用户体验高于一切
I guess philosophically, one was more idealistic and focused on the user experience above all else,
一体化的组织
and was an integrated organization,
而微软则更务实 更模块化
whereas Microsoft much more pragmatic, a modular focus-
这位是 James Allworth That's James Allworth.
他是一位高产的科技作家 曾在苹果零售的企业团队工作
He's a prolific tech writer who worked inside the corporate team of Apple Retail.
注意他对苹果的定义 一个一体化的组织
Notice that definition of Apple he gives. An integrated organization.
那种只对自己负责 不想依赖别人的公司 这是关键
That sense of a company beholden only to itself. A company that doesn't want to rely on others. That's key.
苹果是一家一体化的公司
Apple was the integrated player,
它希望专注于令人愉悦的用户体验
and it wanted to focus on a delightful user experience,
这意味着它希望控制整个技术栈以及交付的一切内容：
and that meant that it wanted to control the entire stack and everything that was delivered,
从硬件到操作系统
from the hardware to the operating system,
甚至运行在操作系统上的应用程序 to even some of the applications that ran on top of the operating system.
新的 重要的创新需要横跨软硬件
And that always served it well in periods where new innovations, important innovations,
才能很好地进入市场
were coming to market where you needed to be across both hardware and software,
当你能够根据自己意愿来改变软件和硬件时
and where being able to change the hardware based on what you wanted to do
你就有了极大的优势
that was new in software was an advantage.
例如
For example-
很多人喜欢这种一体化的模式 并因此成为了苹果的铁杆粉丝
A lot of people loved that integration, and became die hard Apple fans.
不过还有是很多人则选择了微软
Plenty of others stuck with Microsoft.
让我们回到檀香山的销售会议上
Back to that sales conference in Honolulu.
在同一场活动中 乔布斯向观众展示了他即将发布的超级碗广告
At that very same event, Jobs gave his audience a sneak peek at the Superbowl ad he was about to release.
你可能已经亲眼见过这则广告了
You might have seen it for yourself.
想想乔治·奥威尔的 《一九八四》
Think George Orwell's 1984.
在这个冰冷、灰暗的世界里
In this cold and gray world,
无意识的机器人正在独裁者投射的凝视下徘徊
mindless automatons are shuffling along under a dictator's projected gaze.
这些机器人代表 IBM 的用户
They represent IBM users.
然后 代表苹果公司的 漂亮而健美的安娅·梅杰
Then, beautiful, athletic Anya Major, representing Apple,
穿着鲜艳的衣服跑过大厅
comes running through the hall in full color.
她向着老大哥的屏幕猛地投出大锤 将它砸成了碎片
She hurls her sledgehammer at Big Brother's screen, smashing it to bits.
老大哥的咒语解除了
Big Brother's spell is broken,
一个低沉的声音响起 苹果公司要开始介绍麦金塔了
and a booming voice tells us that Apple is about to introduce the Macintosh.
这就是为什么我们的 1984 年 跟小说《一九八四》描写的不一样
And you'll see why 1984 will not be like 1984.
是的 现在回顾那则广告
And yeah, looking back at that commercial,
把苹果说成一个致力于解放大众的自由斗士有点言过其实了
the idea that Apple was a freedom fighter working to set the masses free is a bit much.
但这则广告触动了人们的神经
But the thing hit a nerve.
Ken Segal 曾在为苹果制作这则广告的广告公司工作过
Ken Segal worked at the advertising firm that made the commercial for Apple.
他为史蒂夫·乔布斯工作了十多年
He was Steve Jobs' advertising guy for more than a decade in the early days.
1984 这则广告的负担的风险很大
Well, the 1984 commercial came with a lot of risk.
事实上 它的风险实在太大
In fact, it was so risky
乃至苹果公司在看到它的时候都不想播出它
that Apple didn't want to run it when they saw it.
你可能听说了史蒂夫喜欢它
You've probably heard stories that Steve liked it,
但苹果公司董事会的人并不喜欢它
but the Apple board did not like it.
事实上他们很愤怒 为什么这么多钱被花在这样一件事情上
In fact, they were so outraged that so much money had been spent on such a thing
以至于他们想解雇广告代理商
that they wanted to fire the ad agency.
史蒂夫则为我们公司辩护
Steve was the one sticking up for the agency.
乔布斯一如既往地 慧眼识英雄
Jobs, as usual, knew a good mythology when he saw one.
这则广告在公司内、在业界内都引起了共鸣
That commercial struck such a chord within the company, within the industry,
成为了苹果产品的代表
that it became this thing for Apple.
无论人们那天是否有在购买电脑
Whether or not people were buying computers that day,
它都带来了一种持之以恒的影响
it had a sort of an aura that stayed around for years and years and years,
并让大家在心里定义了这家公司的立场：
and helped define the character of the company.
我们是叛军 我们是拿着大锤的人
We're the rebels. We're the guys with the sledgehammer.
因此 在争夺数十亿潜在消费者心智的过程中
So in their battle for the hearts and minds of literally billions of potential consumers,
苹果公司和微软公司的帝王们正在学着把自己塑造成救世主、
the emperors of Apple and Microsoft were learning to frame themselves as redeemers.
非凡的英雄 选择自己就是选择一种生活方式
As singular heroes. As lifestyle choices.
但比尔·盖茨明白一些苹果难以理解的事情
But Bill Gates knew something that Apple had trouble understanding.
那就是在一个相互连接的世界里
This idea that in a wired world,
没有人   即便他是帝王 能独自完成任务
nobody, not even an emperor, can really go it alone.
1985 年 6 月 25 日
June 25th, 1985.
盖茨给当时的苹果 CEO John Scully 发了一份备忘录
Gates sends a memo to Apple's then CEO John Scully.
那是一个迷失的年代
This was during the wilderness years.
乔布斯刚刚被逐出公司 直到 1996 年才回到苹果
Jobs had just been excommunicated, and wouldn't return to Apple until 1996.
也许正是因为乔布斯离开了 盖茨才敢写这份东西
Maybe it was because Jobs was out that Gates felt confident enough to write what he wrote.
在备忘录中 他鼓励苹果授权制造商分发他们的操作系统
In the memo, he encourages Apple to license their OS to clone makers.
我想读一下备忘录的最后部分
I want to read a bit from the end of the memo,
让你们知道这份备忘录是多么的有洞察力
just to give you a sense of how perceptive it was.
盖茨写道：“如果没有其他个人电脑制造商的支持
Gates writes, "It is now impossible for Apple to create a standard out of their innovative technology
苹果现在不可能让他们的创新技术成为标准
without support from other personal computer manufacturers.
苹果必须开放麦金塔的架构
Apple must open the Macintosh architecture
以获得个人建造商的支持来快速发展和建立标准 ”
to have the independent support required to gain momentum and establish a standard."
换句话说 你们不要再自己玩自己的了
In other words, no more operating in a silo, you guys.
你们必须有与他人合作的意愿
You've got to be willing to partner with others.
你们必须与开发者合作
You have to work with developers.
多年后你依然可以看到这条思想
You see this philosophy years later,
当微软首席执行官史蒂夫·鲍尔默上台做主题演讲时 他开始大喊：
when Microsoft CEO Steve Ballmer gets up on stage to give a keynote and he starts shouting,
“开发者、开发者、开发者、开发者、
"Developers, developers, developers, developers, developers, developers.
开发者、开发者、开发者、开发者、开发者 ”
Developers, developers, developers, developers, developers, developers, developers, developers."
你懂我的意思了吧 微软喜欢开发人员
You get the idea. Microsoft likes developers.
不是说他们打算与开发人员共享源代码
Now, they're not about to share source code with them,
但是他们确实想建立起整个为合作伙伴服务的生态系统
but they do want to build this whole ecosystem of partners.
而当比尔·盖茨建议苹果公司也这么做时
And when Bill Gates suggests that Apple do the same,
如你可能已经猜到的 这个想法被苹果公司抛到了九霄云外
as you might have guessed, the idea is tossed out the window.
苹果划清了界限
Apple had drawn a line in the sand,
五个月后 微软发布了 Windows 1.0
and five months after they trashed Gates' memo, Microsoft released Windows 1.0.
战争开始了
The war was on.
开发者、开发者、开发者、开发者、
Developers, developers, developers, developers,
developers, developers, developers, developers,
开发者、开发者、开发者、开发者、
开发者、开发者、开发者、开发者、开发者、开发者
developers, developers, developers, developers, developers, developers.
你正在收听的是来自红帽公司的原创播客《代码英雄》
You're listening to Command Line Heroes, an original podcast from Red Hat.
本集是第一集 我们将回到过去 重温操作系统战争的史诗
In this inaugural episode, we go back in time to relive the epic story of the OS wars,
我们将会发现 科技巨头之间的战争
and we're going to find out, how did a war between tech giants
是如何为我们今天所生活的开源世界开辟前路的
clear the way for the open source world we all live in today?
好的 让我们先来个背景故事吧
Okay, a little backstory.
如果你已经听过了也请别介意 它实在是经典
And forgive me if you've heard this one, but it's a classic.
当时是 1979 年
It's 1979,
史蒂夫·乔布斯开车去帕洛阿尔托的施乐公园研究中心
and Steve Jobs drives up to the Xerox Park research center in Palo Alto.
那里的工程师一直在为他们所谓的图形用户界面
The engineers there have been developing this whole fleet of elements
开发一系列的元素
for what they call a graphical user interface.
也许你听说过
Maybe you've heard of it.
它们有菜单、滚动条、按钮、文件夹和层叠的窗口
They've got menus, they've got scroll bars, they've got buttons and folders and overlapping windows.
这是对计算机界面的一个前所未有的美丽新设想
It was a beautiful new vision of what a computer interface could look like. And nobody had any of this stuff.
作家兼记者 Steve Levy 谈到了它的潜力
Author and journalist Steven Levy talks about its potential.
有很多人为这个新界面令人感到激动
There was a lot of excitement about this new interface
它比以前的交互界面更友好
that was going to be much friendlier than what we had before,
以前用的交互界面被称为命令行
which used what was called the command line,
这不是在现实生活中使用的交互方式
where there was really no interaction between you and the computer in the way you'd interact with something in real life.
鼠标和电脑上的图像
The mouse and the graphics on the computer gave you a way to do that,
让你可以像指向现实生活中的东西一样 指向电脑上的东西
to point to something just like you'd point to something in real life.
这让事情变得简单多了 你不需要记住那些代码
It made it a lot easier. You didn't have to memorize all these codes.
不过 施乐的高管们并没有意识到他们正坐在白金矿上
Except, the Xerox executives did not get that they were sitting on top of a platinum mine.
一如既往地 工程师比主管们更清楚它的价值
The engineers were more aware than the execs. Typical.
因此那些工程师
So those engineers were, yeah,
在被要求向乔布斯展示这些东西是如何工作时 有点紧张
a little stressed out that they were instructed to show Jobs how everything worked.
然而这毕竟是高管的命令
But the executives were calling the shots.
用乔布斯的话来说 他认为
Jobs felt, quote,
“这个天才产品本来能够让施乐公司垄断整个行业
"The product genius that brought them to that monopolistic position
却被公司的经营者毁了
gets rotted out by people running these companies
因为他们对产品的好坏没有概念 ”
that have no conception of a good product versus a bad product."
这话有些苛刻
That's sort of harsh,
但是 乔布斯带着一卡车施乐高管忽视的想法离开了会议
but hey, Jobs walked out of that meeting with a truckload of ideas that Xerox executives had missed.
这几乎包含了所有他革新桌面计算体验需要的东西
Pretty much everything he needed to revolutionize the desktop computing experience.
1983 年 苹果发布了 Lisa 电脑
Apple releases the Lisa in 1983,
1984 年又发布了 Mac 电脑
and then the Mac in 1984.
这些设备的创意都是抄袭自施乐公司的
These devices are made by the ideas swiped from Xerox.
让我感兴趣的是
What's interesting to me
乔布斯对控诉他偷了图形用户界面的反应
is Jobs' reaction to the claim that he stole the GUI.
他对此很冷静
He's pretty philosophical about it.
他引用毕加索的话：“好的艺术家抄袭 伟大的艺术家偷窃 ”
He quotes Picasso, saying, "Good artists copy, great artists steal."
他告诉一位记者 “我们总是无耻地窃取伟大的创意 ”
He tells one reporter, "We have always been shameless about stealing great ideas."
伟大的艺术家偷窃 好吧
Great artists steal. Okay.
我的意思是 我们说的并不是严格意义上的“偷窃”
I mean, we're not talking about stealing in a hard sense.
没人拿到了专有的源代码
Nobody's obtaining proprietary source code
并公然将其集成到他们自己的操作系统中去
and blatantly incorporating it into their operating system.
这事情更温和些 更像是创意的借用
This is softer, more like idea borrowing.
但乔布斯自己即将学到 这东西很难以控制
And that's much more difficult to control, as Jobs himself was about to learn.
传奇的软件奇才、真正的代码英雄
Andy Hertzfeld
Legendary software wizard, and true command line hero, Andy Hertzfeld,
就是麦金塔开发团队的最初成员
was an original member of the Macintosh development team.
是的 微软是麦金塔电脑软件的第一个合作伙伴
Yeah, Microsoft was our first software partner with the Macintosh.
当时 我们并没有把他们当成是竞争对手
At the time, we didn't really consider them a competitor.
他们是苹果之外 我们第一家交付麦金塔电脑原型的公司
They were the very first company outside of Apple that we gave Macintosh prototypes to.
我通常每周都会和微软的技术主管聊一次
I talked with the technical lead at Microsoft usually once a week.
他们是第一个试用我们所编写软件的外部团队
They were the first outside party trying out the software that we wrote.
他们给了我们非常重要的反馈
They gave us very important feedback,
总的来说 我认为我们的关系非常好
and in general I would say the relationship was pretty good.
但我也注意到 在我与技术主管的交谈中
But I also noticed in my conversations with the technical lead,
他开始问一些系统实现方面的问题 而他本无需知道这些
he started asking questions that he didn't really need to know about how the system was implemented,
我觉得他们想要复制麦金塔电脑
and I got the idea that they were trying to copy the Macintosh.
我很早以前就向史蒂夫·乔布斯反馈过这件事
I told Steve Jobs about it pretty early on,
但在 1983 年秋天 这件事发展到了高潮
but it really came to a head in the fall of 1983.
我们发现 他们没有提前告诉我们
We discovered that they actually, without telling us ahead of time,
就在 1983 年 11 月的 COMDEX 上发布了 Windows
they announced Windows at the COMDEX in November 1983
对此史蒂夫·乔布斯勃然大怒
and Steve Jobs hit the roof.
他认为那是一种背叛
He really considered that a betrayal.
随着新版 Windows 的发布
As newer versions of Windows were released,
很明显 微软从苹果那里学到了
it became pretty clear that Microsoft had lifted from Apple
苹果从施乐那里学来的所有想法
all the ideas that Apple had lifted from Xerox.
乔布斯变得很易怒
Jobs was apoplectic.
他发表的伟大艺术家善于偷窃的毕加索名言被别人学去了
His Picasso line about how great artists steal. Yeah. That goes out the window.
盖茨也正是这么做的
Though maybe Gates was using it now.
据报道 当乔布斯怒斥盖茨偷了他们的东西时 盖茨回应道：
Reportedly, when Jobs screamed at Gates that he'd stolen from them, Gates responded,
“史蒂夫 我觉得这更像是我们都有一个叫施乐的富有邻居
"Well Steve, I think it's more like we both had this rich neighbor named Xerox,
我闯进他家偷电视机
and I broke into his house to steal the TV set,
却发现你已经偷过了”
and found out that you'd already stolen it."
苹果最终以窃取 GUI 的外观和风格为名起诉了微软
Apple ends up suing Microsoft for stealing the look and feel of their GUI.
这个案子持续了好几年
The case goes on for years,
但是在 1993 年 第 9 巡回上诉法院的一名法官
but in 1993, a judge from the 9th Circuit Court of Appeals
最终站在了微软一边
finally sides with Microsoft.
Vaughn Walker 法官宣布外观和风格不受版权保护
Judge Vaughn Walker declares that look and feel are not covered by copyright,
这是非常重要的事情
and this is super important.
这一决定让苹果再无法垄断桌面计算的界面
That decision prevented Apple from creating a monopoly
with the interface that would dominate desktop computing.
很快 苹果短暂的领先优势消失了
Soon enough, Apple's brief lead had vanished.
以下是 Steven Levy 的观点
Here's Steven Levy's take.
他们之所以失去领先地位 不是因为微软方面窃取了知识产权
They lost the lead not because of intellectual property theft on Microsoft's part,
而是因为他们无法巩固自己在上世纪 80 年代就拥有的
but because they were unable to consolidate their advantage
更优越的操作系统的优势
in having a better operating system during the 1980s.
坦率地说 他们的电脑索价过高
They overcharged for their computers, quite frankly.
微软从 20 世纪 80 年代中期开始开发 Windows 系统
So Microsoft had been developing Windows, starting with the mid-1980s,
但直到 1990 年才开发出来 Windows 3
but it wasn't until Windows 3 in 1990, I believe,
我想 这算是第一个开启黄金时代的版本
where they really came across with a version that was ready for prime time.
真正可供大众使用
Ready for masses of people to use.
从此以后 微软能够将数以亿计的用户迁移到图形界面
At that point is where Microsoft was able to migrate huge numbers of people, hundreds of millions,
而这是苹果无法做到的
over to the graphical interface in a way that Apple had not been able to do.
虽然苹果公司有一个非常好的操作系统
Even though they had a really good operating system,
但是那已经是 1984 年的产品了
they used it since 1984.
现在微软主导着操作系统的战场
Microsoft now dominated the OS battlefield.
他们占据了 90% 的市场份额
They held 90% of the market,
并且针对各种各样的个人电脑进行了标准化
and standardized their OS across a whole variety of PCs.
操作系统的未来看起来会由微软掌控
The future of the OS looked like it'd be controlled by Microsoft.
在此后发生了什么？
And then?
1997 年 波士顿 Macworld 博览会上
Well, at the 1997 Macworld Expo in Boston,
你看到了一个几近破产的苹果
you have an almost bankrupt Apple.
一个比之前谦逊得多的史蒂夫·乔布斯走上舞台
A more humble Steve Jobs gets on stage,
开始谈论伙伴关系的重要性
and starts talking about the importance of partnerships,
其中之一已经变得格外重要
and one in particular, he says, has become very, very meaningful.
那就是和微软的合作
Their new partnership with Microsoft.
史蒂夫·乔布斯呼吁双方缓和关系 停止火拼
Steve Jobs is calling for a détente, a ceasefire.
微软将坐享巨大的市场份额
Microsoft could have their enormous market share.
从表面看 我们可能会认为世界和平了
If we didn't know better, we might think we were entering a period of peace in the kingdom.
但当利益如此巨大时 事情就没那么简单了
But when stakes are this high, it's never that simple.
就在苹果和微软在数十年的争斗中伤痕累累、
Just as Apple and Microsoft were finally retreating to their corners,
最终败退到死角之际
pretty bruised from decades of fighting,
一名 21 岁的芬兰计算机科学专业学生出现了
along came a 21-year-old Finnish computer science student
十分偶然的 他彻底改变了一切
who, almost by accident, changed absolutely everything.
我是 Saron Yitbarek 这里是代码英雄
I'm Saron Yitbarek, and this is Command Line Heroes.
正当某些科技巨头正忙着就专有软件相互攻击时
While certain tech giants were busy bashing each other over proprietary software,
自由软件和开源软件的新领军者如雨后春笋般涌现
there were new champions of free and open source software popping up like mushrooms.
其中一位优胜者就是理查德·斯托曼
One of these champions was Richard Stallman.
你也许对他的工作很熟悉
You're probably familiar with his work.
他想要拥有自由软件的自由社会
He wanted free software and a free society.
这就像言论自由一样的自由
That's free as in free speech,
而不是像免费啤酒一样的免费
not free as in free beer.
早在 80 年代 斯托尔曼就发现
Back in the '80s, Stallman saw that
除了昂贵的专有操作系统（如 UNIX）外
there was no viable alternative
没有其他可行的替代品
to pricey, proprietary OSs, like UNIX .
因此他决定自己做一个
So, he decided to make his own.
斯托尔曼的自由软件基金会开发了 GNU
Stallman's Free Software Foundation developed GNU,
当然 它的意思是 “GNU's not UNIX”
which stood for GNU's not UNIX , of course.
它将是一个像 UNIX 一样的操作系统
It'd be an OS like UNIX,
但不包含 UNIX 代码
but free of all UNIX code,
而且所有用户可以自由共享它
and free for users to share.
为了让你体会到上世纪 80 年代自由软件概念的重要性
Just to give you a sense of how important that idea of free software was in the 1980s,
从不同角度来说拥有 UNIX 代码的两家公司
the companies that owned the UNIX code at different points,
AT&T 贝尔实验室以及UNIX 系统实验室
AT&T Bell Laboratories and then UNIX System Laboratories,
威胁将会起诉任何看过 UNIX 源代码后又创建自己操作系统的人
they threatened lawsuits on anyone making their own OS after looking at UNIX source code.
这些人的占有欲简直是另一种层面
These guys were next - level proprietary.
用这两家公司的话来说
All those programmers were,
所有这些程序员都在“精神上受到了污染”
in the words of the two companies, "mentally contaminated,"
因为他们都见过 UNIX 代码
because they'd seen UNIX code.
在 UNIX 系统实验室
In a famous court case
和伯克利软件设计公司之间的一个著名的法庭案例中
between UNIX System Laboratories and Berkeley Software Design,
有人认为即使它本身没有使用 UNIX 代码
it was argued that any functionally similar system,
拥有类似功能的系统也侵犯版权
even though it didn't use the UNIX code itself, was a breach of copyright.
Paul Jones 当时是一名开发人员
Paul Jones was a developer at that time.
他现在是数字图书馆 ibiblio.org 的主管 He's now the director of the digital library ibiblio.org.
他们的观点是 任何看过代码的人 都受到了精神污染
Anyone who has seen any of the code is mentally contaminated was their argument.
因此 几乎所有在安装有与 UNIX 相关操作系统的电脑上工作过的人
And that would have made almost anyone who had worked on a computer operating system that involved UNIX ,
以及任何在计算机科学部门工作的人
and any computer science department that was in the country,
都受到了精神上的污染
was mentally contaminated.
在 USENIX 的一年里
So in one year at USENIX,
我们都得到了一个写着红色字母的白色小别针
we all got little white bar pins with red letters
上面写着“精神受到了污染”
that say mentally contaminated,
我们很喜欢带着这些别针到处走
and we all wear those around to our own great pleasure,
表达我们在这件事上对贝尔实验室的讽刺
to show that we were sticking it to Bell because we were mentally contaminated.
整个世界都被精神污染了
The whole world was getting mentally contaminated.
想要保持纯粹、保持事物的美好
Staying pure, keeping things nice and proprietary,
和完整地拥有一个软件的旧思想正变得越来越不现实
that old philosophy was getting less and less realistic.
正是在这被污染的现实中
It was into this contaminated reality
历史上最伟大的代码英雄之一诞生了
that one of history's biggest command line heroes was born,
他是一个芬兰男孩 名叫林纳斯·托瓦兹
a boy in Finland named Linus Torvalds.
如果这是《星球大战》 那么林纳斯·托瓦兹就是我们的卢克·天行者
If this is Star Wars, then Linus Torvalds is our Luke Skywalker.
他是赫尔辛基大学的一名温文尔雅的研究生
He was a mild-mannered grad student at the University of Helsinki.
有才华 但缺乏大志
Talented, but lacking in grand visions.
典型的被逼上梁山的英雄
The classic reluctant hero.
和其他年轻的英雄一样 他也感到沮丧
And, like any young hero, he was also frustrated.
他想把 386 处理器整合到他的新电脑中
He wanted to incorporate the 386 processor into his new PC's functions.
他对自己兼容 IBM 的电脑上运行 MS-DOS 操作系统并不感冒
He wasn't impressed by the MS-DOS running on his IBM clone,
也负担不起 UNIX 软件 5000 美元的价格
and he couldn't afford the $5,000 price tag on the UNIX software
但只有 UNIX 才能让他自由地编程
that would have given him some programming freedom.
解决方案是 托瓦兹在 1991 年春天
The solution, which Torvalds crafted on MINIX in the spring of 1991,
基于 MINIX 开发了一个名为 Linux 的操作系统内核
was an OS kernel called Linux.
他自己的操作系统内核
The kernel of an OS of his very own.
林纳斯·托瓦兹真的只是想找点乐子而已
Linus Torvalds really just wanted to have something to play with.
Steven Vaughan-Nichols 是 ZDNet.com 的特约编辑
Steven Vaughan-Nichols is a contributing editor at ZDNet.com,
而且他从科技行业出现以来就一直在写科技行业相关的内容
and he's been writing about the business of technology since there was a business of technology.
当时有几个类似的操作系统
There were a couple of operating systems like it at the time.
他最关注的是一个名叫 MINIX
The main one that he was concerned about was called MINIX,
旨在让学生学习如何构建操作系统的项目
and that was an operating system that was meant for students to learn how to build operating systems.
林纳斯看到了这些并且觉得它很有趣
Linus looked at that, and thought that it was interesting,
但他打算建立自己的操作系统
but he wanted to build his own.
所以 Linux 实际上始于赫尔辛基的一个 DIY 项目
So it really started as a do-it-yourself project at Helsinki.
一切就这样开始了
And that's how it all started,
基本上就是一个大孩子在玩耍 学习如何做些什么
it's just basically a big kid playing around and learning how to do things.
但不同之处在于 他足够聪明、足够执着
But what was different in his case is that he was both bright enough and persistent enough,
也足够友好 能让其他人都参与进来
and also friendly enough to get all these other people working on it,
然后他开始把这个项目进行到底
and then he started seeing the project through.
27 年后 这个项目变得比他想象的要大得多
27 years later, it is much, much bigger than he ever dreamed it would be.
到 1991 年秋季 托瓦兹发布了 10000 行代码
By the fall of 1991, Torvalds releases 10,000 lines of code,
世界各地的人们开始评头论足
and people around the world start offering comments,
然后进行优化、添加和修改代码
then tweaks, additions, edits.
对于今天的开发人员来说似乎很正常
That might seem totally normal to you as a developer today,
但请记住 在那个时候
but remember, at that time,
开放协作操作系统是对微软、苹果和 IBM
open collaboration like that was a moral affront to the whole proprietary system
这些靠专利盈利的公司的精神侮辱
that Microsoft, Apple, and IBM had done so well by.
随后这种开放性被奉上神坛
And then that openness gets enshrined.
托瓦兹将 Linux 置于 GNU 通用公共许可证之下
Torvalds places Linux under the GNU general public license.
曾经保障斯托尔曼的 GNU 系统自由的许可证
The license that had kept Stallman's GNU system free
现在也将保障 Linux 的自由
was now going to keep Linux free, too.
GPL 许可基本上能永远保证软件的自由和开放性
The importance of that move to incorporate GPL,
它的重要性被怎么强调都不过分
basically preserving the freedom and openness of the software forever, cannot be overstated.
Vaughan-Nichols 解释道
Vaughan-Nichols explains.
事实上 根据 Linux 所遵循的许可协议
In fact, by the license that it's under,
即 GPL 第 2 版
which is called GPL version 2,
如果你想贩卖 Linux 或者向全世界展示它
you have to share the code
你必须与他人共享代码
if you're going to try to sell it or present it to the world,
所以如果你对其做了一些改进
so that if you make an improvement,
仅仅给别人使用打包的代码是不够的
it's not enough just to give someone the improvement.
你必须和他们分享这些变化的所有细节代码
You actually have to share with them the nuts and bolts of all those changes.
然后这些改进足够好时 也许就会被 Linux 所吸收
Then they are adapted into Linux if they're good enough.
事实证明 这种公开的方式极具吸引力
That public approach proved massively attractive.
埃里克·雷蒙德是这场运动的早期传道者之一 Eric Raymond, one of the early evangelists of the movement
他在他那篇著名的文章中写道：
wrote in his famous essay that,
“微软和苹果这样的公司一直在试图建造软件大教堂
"Corporations like Microsoft and Apple have been trying to build software cathedrals,
而 Linux 及类似的软件则提供了一个
while Linux and its kind were offering a great babbling bazaar
由不同议程和方法组成的巨大集市
of different agendas and approaches.
集市比大教堂有趣多了 ”
The bazaar was a lot more fun than the cathedral."
我认为在那个时候 真正吸引人们的是
I think at the time, what attracted people
他们终于可以掌控这个属于他们的世界了
is that they were going to be in control of their own world.
Stormy Peters 是一位行业分析师
Stormy Peters is an industry analyst,
也是自由和开源软件的倡导者
and an advocate for free and open source software.
当开源软件第一次出现的时候 所有的操作系统都是专有的
When open source software first came out, the OS was all proprietary.
如果不使用专有软件 你甚至不能添加打印机
You couldn't even add a printer without going through proprietary software.
不能添加耳机
You couldn't add a headset.
不能自己开发一个小型硬件设备
You couldn't develop a small hardware device of your own,
然后让它在你的笔记本电脑上运行
and make it work with your laptop.
你甚至不能放入 DVD 并复制它
You couldn't even put in a DVD and copy it,
因为你不能改变软件
because you couldn't change the software.
即使你拥有这张 DVD 你也无法改变它的内容
Even if you owned the DVD, you couldn't copy it.
你无法掌控你购买的硬件 / 软件系统
You had no control over this hardware/software system that you'd bought.
你不能从中创造出任何新的、更大的、更好的东西
You couldn't create anything new and bigger and better out of it.
这就是为什么开源操作系统在一开始就如此重要
That's why an open source operating system was so important at the beginning.
我们需要一个开源协作环境 在那里我们可以构建更大更好的东西
We needed an open source collaborative environment where we could build bigger and better things.
请注意 Linux 并不是一个纯粹的平等乌托邦
Mind you, Linux isn't a purely egalitarian utopia.
林纳斯·托瓦兹并没有负责批准所有对内核的修改
Linus Torvalds doesn't approve everything that goes into the kernel,
但他主导了内核的变更
but he does preside over its changes.
他安排了十几个人来管理内核的不同部分
He's installed a dozen or so people below him to manage different parts of the kernel.
这些人也会信任自己下面的人 以此类推 形成信任金字塔
They, in turn, trust people under themselves, and so on, in a pyramid of trust.
变化可能来自任何地方 但它们都经过了判断和策划
Changes might come from anywhere, but they're all judged and curated.
然而 考虑到到林纳斯的 DIY 项目一开始是多么的简陋和随意
It is amazing, though, to think how humble, and kind of random,
这项成就令人十分惊讶
Linus' DIY project was to begin with.
他完全不知道自己就是这一切中的卢克·天行者
He didn't have a clue he was the Luke Skywalker figure in all this.
当时他只有 21 岁 已经编程了半辈子
He was just 21, and had been programming half his life.
不过当魔盒第一次被打开时 人们开始给他反馈
But this was the first time the silo opened up, and people started giving him feedback.
几十个 然后几百个 成千上万的贡献者
Dozens, then hundreds, and thousands of contributors.
有了这样的众包基础 Linux 很快就开始成长 而且成长得很快
With crowdsourcing like that, it doesn't take long before Linux starts growing. Really growing.
甚至最终引起了微软的注意
It even finally gets noticed by Microsoft.
他们的首席执行官史蒂夫·鲍尔默将 Linux 称为是
Their CEO, Steve Ballmer, called Linux, and I quote,
“一种癌症 从知识产权的角度来看 它传染了任何它接触的东西”
"A cancer that attaches itself in an intellectual property sense to everything it touches."
Steven Levy 将会描述 Ballmer 的立场
Steven Levy describes where Ballmer was coming from.
一旦微软真正巩固了它的垄断地位
Once Microsoft really solidified its monopoly,
而且它也确实被联邦法院判定为垄断
and indeed it was judged in federal court as a monopoly,
他们将会对任何可能对其构成威胁的事情做出强烈反应
anything that could be a threat to that, they reacted very strongly to.
他们很自然的将自由软件看成是一种癌症
So of course, the idea that free software would be emerging,
因为微软要通过软件来赚钱
when they were charging for software, they saw as a cancer.
他们试图提出一个知识产权理论
They tried to come up with an intellectual property theory
来解释为什么开源对消费者不利
about why this was going to be bad for consumers.
Linux 在不断传播 微软也开始担心起来
Linux was spreading, and Microsoft was worried.
到了 2006 年 Linux 成为仅次于 Windows 的第二大常用操作系统
By 2006, Linux would become the second most widely used operating system after Windows,
约有 5000 名开发者在世界各地开发它
with about 5,000 developers working on it worldwide.
5000 名开发者
Five thousand.
还记得比尔·盖茨给苹果公司的备忘录吗？
Remember that memo that Bill Gates sent to Apple,
在那份备忘录中 他向苹果公司的员工们论述了与他人合作的重要性
the one where he's lecturing them about the importance of partnering with other people?
事实证明 开源将把伙伴关系的概念提升到一个全新的水平
Turns out, open source would take that idea of partnerships to a whole new level,
这是比尔·盖茨从未预见到的
in a way Bill Gates would have never foreseen.
我们一直在谈论操作系统之间的大战
We've been talking about these huge battles for the OS,
但是到目前为止 无名英雄和开发者们还没有完全介入战场
but so far, the unsung heroes, the developers, haven't fully made it onto the battlefield.
在下集中 情况就不同了
That changes next time, on Command Line Heroes.
第二集讲的还是操作系统大战 关于 Linux 崛起的第二部分 In episode two, part two of the OS wars, it's the rise of Linux.
资本们醒悟过来 认识到了开发人员的重要性
Businesses wake up, and realize the importance of developers.
这些开源反叛者变得越来越强大
These open source rebels grow stronger,
战场从桌面转移到了服务器领域
and the battlefield shifts from the desktop to the server room.
这里有商业间谍活动、新的英雄人物
There's corporate espionage, new heroes,
还有科技史上最不可思议的改变
and the unlikeliest change of heart in tech history.
这一切都在操作系统大战的后半集内达到了高潮
It all comes to a head in the concluding half of the OS wars.
在这一季剩下的时间里 我们将参观最新的战场
Over the rest of the season, we're visiting the latest battlefields,
相互争斗的版图 这里是下一代的代码英雄留下印记的地方
the up-for-grab territories where the next generation of Command Line Heroes are making their mark.
代码英雄是一款红帽公司原创的博客节目
Command Line Heroes is an original podcast from Red Hat.
更多信息 请访问https://www.redhat.com/en/command-line-heroes
For more info, check us out at redhat.com/commandlineheroes.
我是 Saron Yitbarek 感谢收听 请坚持编程
I'm Saron Yitbarek. Thanks for listening, and keep on coding.